So today I'm-- it's my pleasure
to welcome Joshua Batson from
Anthropic.
So he'll be talking about on
the biology of a large language
model, which should be
a very interesting talk.
So Josh leads the
circuits effort
of the Anthropic mechanistic
interpretability team.
Before Anthropic, he
worked on viral genomics
and computational microscopy
at the Chan Zuckerberg biohub.
And his academic training is
in pure mathematics, which
is very cool and impressive.
And just another thing,
which is some more recordings
for this quarter have released
like Karina and Dave's talks.
So feel free to check those
out on our YouTube playlist.
And for the folks on
Zoom, feel free to ask
questions, either on the Zoom
or the Slido with the code CS25.
And without further ado,
I'll hand it off to Josh.
Thank you.
Clap.
Come on, we're getting started.
[APPLAUSE]
It's a pleasure to be here.
It's crazy to me that there
was a class on transformers
now, which I think, were
invented rather recently.
We've got like, an
hour for the class,
I guess, and then 15, 20
minutes for questions.
Feel free to just interrupt
me with questions.
As you said, my training is in
pure mathematics and people just
interrupt each other all
the time, very rudely
and it's totally fine.
And so if I want to just cut you
off and move on to something,
I will.
But this can be as interactive
as you guys would like it to be.
And that's true for
the people on Zoom too.
So this talk is titled on the
biology of a large language
model, which is also
the title of a paper,
which is what we call our
100-page interactive blog post
that went out a few weeks ago.
And if you're here, you
probably know something
about large language models.
The biology word is like--
was our choice here.
And maybe you should contrast
it to a series of papers called
on the physics of large
language models, where you're
thinking of them as
dynamical systems
over the course of training.
But we think of interpretability
being in relationship
to neural networks as which are
trained by gradient descent.
As biology is to
living systems that
are developed through evolution.
So you have some process that
gives rise to complexity.
And you can just
study the objects
that are produced for how
they do the miraculous things
that they do.
So models do lots
of cool things.
I don't need to
tell you guys this.
This is an example.
Oh, I don't know when it's from
now, maybe six months ago, which
is like 10 years in AI time.
But I quite enjoyed this.
This was just somebody who was
working on natural language
processing for Circassian, which
is like a very low resource
language.
Not many people speak it.
There's not many documents.
And he'd been tracking the
state of the art in NLP
for many years, like using
the best models at the time
to try to just help
translate into this language,
translate from this
language, help preserve it,
and tried it with a
version of Claude,
where I think this was
probably [INAUDIBLE]
3.5, where he just
shoved this master
list of Russian
Circassian translations
into the context window.
So just like painstakingly
gathered over years,
rather than train a model, just
put it in the context window
and then just ask the model
to do other translations.
And it could not only translate
it successfully, but also
break down the grammar.
And so just in context,
learning with these models
was enough to beat
the state of the art
for the NLP specific
models that he'd
been working on for a while.
So like that's cool would
be my summary of that.
But models are also weird.
So this is also Claude
and someone asked her what
day is tomorrow on leap day.
And it's just like
got in a big fight.
If today is February 29, 2024,
then tomorrow would be March 1.
However, 2024 is not a
leap year, which is untrue.
So February 29 is not a valid
date in the Gregorian calendar.
OK, now it starts throwing out
the rules following this rule.
2000 is a leap year.
2100 will not be like fine.
And then it says the
next leap year after 2024
will be 2028, which is true.
And then so if we assume
you meant February 28, 2024,
the last valid date
in February, then
it gives-- it is just
like, what is going on?
There's some smorgasborg of
correct recollection of facts,
correct reasoning from
the facts and then
disregarding them out of
consistency with this initial.
It's just pretty weird
for it to be leap day.
So like that's odd.
I mean, if a person were
doing this, you would wonder,
what was in the brownies
they had consumed.
There's just this-- now,
children are of this.
So maybe that's an
interesting topic.
And then I just love this.
AI will make designers obsolete.
AI accepted the job and
it's got so many fingers.
This is now out of date.
People have figured out how
to keep the finger count down
to at most 5 per hand.
The new ChatGPT model can do
extremely realistic people.
And they all have
five fingers now.
But that wasn't exactly
solved by figuring out,
why are there so many fingers
on these just other methods got
through.
But presumably, you bat
down some of this weirdness
and now it's just the weirdness
is more sophisticated.
So as the models
get better, you need
to get better at
understanding just
where the craziness has gone.
So as the frontier
moves forward,
maybe it's not five
fingers, but there
might be subtly other
things that are wrong.
And when I think about
interpretability,
which is what did the
model lear exactly,
how is it represented
inside the model,
how does it manifest
in behaviors?
I am thinking ahead to when
most of the simple interactions
seem to go well, and then it's
like, are they going well?
Because fundamentally
the model learns
something like deep and
true, or because you've
managed to beat this down
like the finger problem.
But if you went out to the edge
of the model's capabilities,
it would all be seven fingers
again, but you can't tell.
And also because it
seems pretty reliable,
you've delegated a lot of
decision making and trust
to these models, and
it's in the corner.
You can no longer verify
where things get weird.
So for that reason, we want
to understand what's going on
with these capabilities.
All right.
So this will be a bit of a
review at the beginning of why
models are hard to understand,
some strategies for picking them
apart and then-- and
then three main lessons,
I think, we've learned
about how models work inside
that aren't obvious from a black
box way of engaging with them.
So here are three
statements that
are somewhere between
myths or things
that are out of date or true if
you interpret them in one way,
philosophically, but
missing the point.
And so these statements that
models just pattern match
to similar training
data examples
that they use only like
shallow and simple heuristics
and reasoning, and that they
just work one word at a time,
just gutting out the next
thing and some eruption
of spontaneity.
And I think we find that
models learn and can compose
pretty abstract representations
inside that they
perform rather complex and often
heavily parallel computations.
It's not serials that they're
doing a bunch of things at once
at the same time, and also
that they plan many tokens
into the future.
So even though they
say one word at a time,
they're often thinking
ahead quite far
to be able to make
something coherent, which
will work for that.
OK.
This is probably a
review for this class,
but we made these nice slides.
And I think it's nice
to go through anyway.
So you have a chatbot
which is hello, how can I
assist you as an answer.
How does this actually happen?
It is saying one word
at a time by just
predicting the next word.
So how goes through
Claude and predicts
can and how can goes to I
and how can I goes to assist
and how can I assist
goes to you so you
can reduce the problem to the
computation that gives you
the next word.
And that is a neural network.
Here I've drawn like a
fully connected network
to turn language into language.
Passing through numbers, you
have to turn things into vectors
first.
So there's the embeddings.
So every word or token
in the vocabulary
has an embedding, which is a
list of numbers or a vector.
Morally speaking, you basically
just concatenate those together
and run them through a
massive neural network
with a lot of weights,
outcomes, a score
for every word in the
vocabulary and the model
says the highest scoring
word modulo some temperature
to introduce randomness.
Transformer architectures
are more complex.
There's these
residual connections,
alternating attention and MLP
blocks, which you could think
of as baking in a really strong
priors into a massive MLP.
But in some sense that's
just about efficiency.
So a metaphor we found useful,
which is also biological,
is that language models
should be thought of as grown,
not built. You start with this
randomly initialized thing
and architecture, which
is like a scaffold.
You like give it some data,
maybe that's like a nutrient.
And then the loss is like the
sun and it grows towards that.
And so you get this
organic thing which
has been made by the end of it.
But the way that it
grew, you don't really
have any access to it.
The scaffold you have access to.
But that's like
looking at a model
at a net, which tends not
to be that interesting.
So of course, we have
the models and so--
and so there is a
tautological answer
to what are they doing,
which I already told you,
which is they turn the
words into numbers.
They do a bunch of matmuls.
They apply simple functions.
It's just math all
the way through.
And then you get something
out and it's like, that's it.
That's what the model does.
And I think that's an
unsatisfying answer because you
can't reason about it.
That answer to
how do models work
doesn't tell you
about what behaviors
they should or shouldn't be able
to do or any of those things.
So the first thing
you might hope
is that the neurons
inside the neural network
might have interpretable roles.
People were hoping that's going
back to the first networks
in the 80s.
And there was a
bit of a resurgence
in deep learning, a small one.
Chris Olah, who leads
the team at Anthropic,
got really into
this 10 years ago.
You just look at
a neuron and you
ask, when does
this fire for what
inputs is this neuron active.
And then you just see do
those form a coherent class.
This is the car detector
neuron in the vision model
or this is the eye detector or
this is like the edge detector
if it's early in the model.
They found the Donald Trump
neuron in a CLIP model,
for example.
But it turns out that
in language models when
you do this, you just
say which sentences
cause this neuron to activate.
The answer doesn't
make that much sense.
So here's a visualization
of a bunch of example texts
for which a neuron
in a model activates.
And there's just a lot of stuff.
There's code and some Chinese
and some math and hemlock
for Socrates.
It's not especially clear.
And of course, there's no reason
it would need to be, right.
It's just learned a function.
And so asking for a
neuron to be interpretable
is like a bit of a Hail Mary.
And it's pretty cool
that works sometimes,
but it's not
particularly systematic.
So there's a prior--
a prior from neuroscience
is that maybe while there's
a whole bunch of
neurons going on
or something that
in any given moment
maybe the model is not thinking
of that many things at once.
Maybe there is some
sparsity here where
if there were a map of the
concepts the model is using
or the subroutines
it's using or something
that on any given token, it's
only using a few at a time.
And that's just maybe
a slightly better guess
than maybe the neurons
are interpretable.
It's not necessarily
a great prior,
but it's something
you can work with.
And so you can fit linear
combinations of neurons
such that each activation
vector is a sparse combination
of these dictionary elements.
This is called dictionary
learning classical ML.
And we just did it.
So you just gather a
bunch of activations
from the model when you put
through a trillion texts
or something and then
you take those vectors,
you look for
dictionaries and then
you look at when are those
dictionary components active.
And Lo and behold,
it's way better.
So we had a paper
last year, which
was just like here's
a bunch of them where
we fit about 30 million
features on Claude 3
Sonnet on the middle
layer of the model.
So you just say,
what are the atoms
of computation or representation
inside that model?
This was one of my favorites,
where this linear combination
is present, or it's like
a dot product with vector
is large when the input is
about the Golden Gate Bridge.
And that is true if it
is an explicit mention
of the Golden Gate Bridge
in English on the left.
Also, true if it's translated
into another language.
Also, true if it's an image
of the Golden Gate Bridge.
Also, true it turns out if
it's an indirect mention.
So you're like, I was driving
from San Francisco to Marin,
which you crossed
the bridge to do.
And the same feature
is active there.
So it's some relatively general
concept also in San Francisco
landmarks, et cetera.
So these combinations of
neurons are interpretable.
We were happy with this.
There's things that are
more abstract notions
of inner conflict.
There was a feature
for bugs in code
that fired on small
bugs like division
by zeros or typos or something
in many different programming
languages.
If you suppressed
it, the model would
act like there wasn't a bug.
If you activated it, the model
would give you a traceback
as if there were a bug.
And so it had this
general properties.
But there was something very
unsatisfying about this,
which is like, how does it know
it's the Golden Gate bridge?
And so what?
What does it do with
that information?
So even if you manage to piece
apart the representations,
that's just a cross section.
It doesn't give you
the why and the how.
It just gives you what.
And so we wanted to
find ways of connecting
these features together.
So you start from
the input words
and you're going to process
these to higher order
representations.
And eventually it
will say something.
And trying to trace
that through--
[INAUDIBLE] through
optimization.
So very concretely,
you have a matrix,
which is like you take a billion
examples of activation vectors,
and then you've
got D model here.
That's a matrix.
And you try to factorize that
matrix into a product of a fixed
dictionary of atoms times a
sparse matrix of which atoms
are present in which example.
And you just have an
objective function,
which is this should reconstruct
the data and some L1 penalty
to encourage sparsity.
[INAUDIBLE]
It's a joint
optimization problem.
Yeah, that's right,
that's right.
We tried being
clever about this.
There's a beautiful,
rich literature
on dictionary learning.
But after a few months of
that the bitter lesson got us.
And it turned out that you could
just use a one layer sparse
autoencoder, which you can put
in [INAUDIBLE] and then just
train on your GPUs.
And like that scaling was more
important than being clever
yet again.
So that's what it is.
It's a sparse autoencoder.
All right.
So here's a prompt.
So the capital of the state
containing Dallas is Austin.
This is true.
That's because the state
containing Dallas is Texas.
Good.
Did the model do that?
Was it like Texas.
So Austin or is it like--
I don't know-- it's seen
a lot of training data.
Was this just in it?
And it's just like
reciting the answer.
People-- there's a lot
of eval contamination.
A lot of [INAUDIBLE] made it
into people's training sets.
So you get high scores.
Well, just knew the
answer to that literally,
because it had seen it.
So did it literally see
this before or is it
kind of thinking
Texas like you did?
It's thinking about Texas.
So I'll tell you, this
is like a cartoon.
And we can slowly
through this pick,
break away these abstractions
to literally what we did.
But I'll start by saying
that you should think
of each of these as bundles
of features which are again,
atoms we learned through
an optimization process.
We label the role
of each feature
by looking at when
it's active and trying
to see if we can
describe in language
what that feature is doing.
And then the
connections between them
are actually direct
causal connections
as the model processes
this in a forward pass.
And so what we do is we break
apart the model into pieces.
We ask which pieces are active,
can we interpret them SEPARATELY
And then how does it flow.
And so in this case, we found
a bunch of features related
to capitals, a bunch
related to states
in the abstract, a
bunch related to Dallas.
We found some features
that were-- you
can think of as motor neurons.
They make the
model do something.
In this case, they make it
say the name of a capital
like they make it say a bunch
of state capitals or country
capitals or something.
So that's a start.
But also it has to get it right.
And so there's some mapping
from Dallas into Texas.
And there's a pile
of features there.
Some are discussions
of Texas politics.
Some are like phrases like,
everything's bigger in Texas.
And once you have
Texas in a capital,
you get saying
Austin in particular.
And if you're saying
a state capital
and also you're saying
Austin, what you get
is like Austin coming out.
There's some interesting
straight lines though,
so Texas also feeds
into Austin directly.
If you're thinking about
Texas, you might just
be thinking about Austin.
And so I'll get into more
of how we build this.
But this gives you
a picture in terms
of these atoms or dictionary
elements we've learned.
And you might want to
check that they make sense.
So then you can do interventions
on the model deleting
pieces of this.
In neuroscience these
would be ablations
of neurons or something.
And then you see if
the output of the model
changes as you would expect.
Someone on Zoom asked words that
also frequently appear together
in internet context, suggesting
simple statistical correlations.
So is this a way of
overcomplicating things?
I think that people have
found that transformers
have outperformed
[INAUDIBLE] for most tasks.
So Houston also occurs with
Dallas and the training data.
And the model
doesn't say Houston.
So it must be using
the capital and Dallas.
In this case, I think
you could say maybe
if you just had
capital and Dallas,
then it would say Austin.
And that's actually
true, I think.
Some of these edges
are pretty weak.
And it turns out you could
just say the capital,
you make something
ungrammatical,
just like the capital of Dallas
is and it will say Austin.
And that's an
interesting thing where
I think you look at the
graph and this edge is weak,
and it indicates that
actually maybe it
is just if you have
capital in Dallas
and proximity, you
might get Austin,
which is then causally true.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
I mean, the capital is
a neural network layer
and the bottom layer.
Yeah.
My understanding is correct?
So this is the flow through
layers of the model.
OK.
Upstairs.
And we've done
some grouping here.
So I will show in more detail.
Let me actually see what
we're going to get to that.
Yeah.
So I'm going to give you a
lot more detail in just about
a slide on the
technical side Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
We did a scan where we trained
dictionaries of different sizes.
And we-- you get some trade off
of obviously, the compute you
spend and the amount or the
accuracy of the approximation.
These are supposed to
reconstruct the activations.
How well does that happen?
The bigger the dictionary
the better it does.
Also, the denser it is
the less sparse it is,
the better that does.
But you pay some price on
interpretability at some point.
So we did a bunch
of sweeps and then
we picked something
that seems good enough.
There's still a bunch of errors.
And I'll show you later
how those show up to--
I mean that we can't
explain a lot of things.
OK.
I'm going to go on.
So yeah, literally
what we do here
is train this sparse
replacement model.
So the basic idea is you have
a model of residual stream
go through [INAUDIBLE].
We're going to forget
about attention right now.
And we're going to try
to approximate that
with these cross-layer
transcoders.
And so what do I mean by that?
So transcoder is something
that moves information.
So it emulates the MLPs.
But the cross layer is
this ensemble of them
emulates all the MLPs.
There's an architecture called
DenseNet from a few years ago,
where every layer writes
to every subsequent layer.
And this is like that.
So the basic idea is that
this ensemble of CLTs
have to take in the inputs of
all the MLPs stack together
and produce the vector of
all of their outputs at once.
And a reason to do this is like
there's no particular reason
to think that the atomic
units of computation
have to live in one layer.
If there's two consecutive
layers in a deep model,
those neurons are
almost interchangeable.
People have done experiments.
You can actually swap the
order of transformer layers
without damaging
performance that much,
which means that indexing that
hard on the existing layer
is maybe unwise.
So we just say, OK, these
can skip to the end.
This ends up making the
interpretability easier
because sometimes it's
just bigram statistics.
I see this word.
I say that word that's
evident at layer 1,
but you have to keep propagating
it all the way through
to get it out.
And so here we
could make that be
one feature instead
of dozens of features
in consecutive
layers interacting.
And then we just train
that optimization.
You've got a loss on accuracy
and a loss on sparsity.
And so here we replaced the
neurons with these features.
We used just the attention
from the base models.
We do not try to
explain attention.
We just flow through it.
But we try to explain
what the MLPs are doing.
And now instead of
the neurons, which
are of uninterpretable
like on the left here,
we have stuff that makes
more sense on the right.
This is say, a capital
feature, and I think
it's probably more specific.
So this is like in these literal
state to capital mappings.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
So I don't know.
Reasonable, I'd
say it's expedient.
It loses a lot.
I think that from a practical
perspective, though,
if you want to model the
action of the attention layer
or anything that moves
information between tokens,
then the input would have
to be the activations at all
of the token positions.
And here we only can do one
token position at a time.
So you learn something
much simpler.
And I think the learning problem
is just a lot-- a lot easier.
It's also like slightly
less clear what the thing
to replace the
attention layer is
that it would be
interpretable because it needs
to be a system for both
transforming information
and moving it.
And sparsity isn't a
good priority there.
You've got like a four tensor
instead of a two tensor,
and we aren't sure what
the right answer is.
So we just did this for now.
[INAUDIBLE]
--your interpretation of what
the relevant features are?
So there's two questions there.
One is like what do you
lose by doing a replacement?
And the other is
like how much are you
leaning on your interpretations
of the components you get.
And what is a relevant feature?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Well, so the sparse autoencoder
just produces a bunch of these.
But we do have to
interpret what comes out.
And so for any particular
graph, we can go--
we have now the
attention is frozen.
We have a forward
pass of the model
through the replacement,
where you've
got a bunch of the features.
We've got these
triangles represent
these diamonds are the errors.
So like these don't perfectly
reconstruct the base model.
So you have to
include an error term.
And then you can just track
the influence directly.
These are just linear maps
until you get to the end.
And there'll be a
lot of these active
fewer than there are neurons.
But order 100 per token.
But they don't all matter
for the model's output.
So then you can go from the
output Austin here backwards
and say which features were
directly, causally relevant
for saying Austin and then
which features were causally
relevant for those being active
and then which are causally
relevant, those being active.
And in way, you get
a much smaller thing,
something you could
actually look at
to try to understand why it
said this literal thing here.
And now, you're-- but
this is all still math.
Now, you have this graph, but
if you want to interpret this,
then you need to look at
these individual components
and see if you can
make sense of them.
And now you're back
to looking at when
was this active in which
examples hoping that's
interpretable and that the
connections between them
make any sense.
Often these will be in
some rough categories.
So here's one Texas feature
is like again, everything's
bigger in Texas.
Texas is a big state known
for its cowboys and cowgirls.
And this other one
is about politics
and the judicial system.
And I'm not saying that
these are the right way
to break apart the
network, but they are a way
to break apart the network.
And if you look at
the flow in here,
these Texas features feed
into say, Austin ones.
There is a path here.
And so we will
manually group some
of these based on at this
point, human interpretation
to get a map of what's going on.
Yeah.
These are Zoom question.
In CLT architecture, we
freeze attention blocks
and replace MLPs
with transcoders
that speak to each other.
This is complex.
So won't this be adding
unnecessary interpretability
when the underlying connections
could be a lot simpler?
Also, do you mind repeating the
question so the folks on Zoom
can hear.
Yes the question is, boy, this
seems a lot of extra work.
There's a lot of connections
between these features.
They're mediated by attention.
And I would agree.
But we couldn't find a
way of doing less work
and have the units
be interpretable.
One way to think about this as
the base components of the model
aren't that interpretable.
So if you want to
interpret things
as interactions of
components, if you
want to use the great
reductionist strategy,
that's been quite effective,
but break organs into cells
and understand how
the cells interact,
you have to break it
apart in some way.
You lose a lot when
you do that, but you
gain something, which is you can
talk about how those parts work.
And so this was our best
guess today as parts to study.
So we're still in
schematic land here.
Once we have grouped things
to make a graph like this,
we can do interventions.
And these interventions
are in the base model
not in our complicated
replacement model.
They amount to
basically adding in
vectors that are the feature
outputs to another one.
And you can see if the
perturbations make sense.
So if we swap out the
texts by muting those
and add in the California
features from another prompt,
then the model will
say Sacramento.
If you put in Georgia,
it will say Atlanta.
If you put in the
Byzantine Empire,
it will say Constantinople.
And so here it's a sign that we
did capture an abstract thing
in a manipulable way.
You don't put it in
and get gibberish.
If you're just doing bigram
statistics or something,
it's not clear how you
would get this separability.
So I'm going to get into these
three motifs that we see a lot.
The abstract representations
in a medical context,
in a multilingual context
parallel processing motifs,
which is about arithmetic, some
jailbreaks and hallucinations,
and then also some
elements of planning.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] you don't
have a certain scale or do
they appear like
smaller [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
So this approach of
training, a replacement
model of an analyzing an
attribute graph is just math.
So you can do whatever you want.
And then it's like, are they
interpretable is the question.
We do this on a small
18 layer model in one
of the papers, which
can't do very much
and find pretty
interpretable things.
So I think this
works at all scales.
I know people who
are doing these
on how interesting is it if
your model can't do anything.
Maybe it's not that
interesting, but I
think if your model is
narrow purpose and small,
this would still be useful.
[INAUDIBLE] biology
here and this all
seems like something that
maybe in a different field
has been done to human brains
and [INAUDIBLE] do you know
is there any overlap
on literature
that you are relying on from the
real medicine side of things?
For some inspiration,
I think in particular
this the idea of doing
the perturbation,
the causal perturbations
and seeing what happens
is like a very neuroscience
optogenetics thing to do.
Fortunately or unfortunately,
like our experimental setup
is so much better than theirs.
So I think we're now
well past what people
can do in neuroscience
because we have one brain
and we can study
it a billion times
and we can intervene on
everything and measure
everything.
And they're like trying to
capture 0.1% of neurons,
like at a time resolution 1,000
times worse than the actual
activity.
So yeah.
Maybe the other way
around that [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
I want to give you just--
I think it's good to be able
to actually see some of these.
So this is in the paper itself.
This is like what we
make these cartoons from.
So each of these nodes is
like a feature and an edge
is like a causal influence.
Here's one whose direct
effect on the output
is saying Austin mostly,
and also some Texas things.
It's getting inputs
from things related
to Texas and from states.
And these-- the art of
this is like now you're
doing the interpretation.
You're like bouncing around,
looking at these components,
looking at when they're active,
looking at what they connect to
and trying to figure
out what's going on.
And so the cartoons
I'll show you
are given by grouping
sets of these
based on common properties.
So I said, these
were, say, a capital.
And you can see that these
are different from each other,
but they all do involve
the models, saying capitals
in some context.
And so we just piled those
on top of each other.
And this is what--
I don't know-- how many
features should you have?
I don't know.
There's obviously no right
answer here, I think.
It's not a perfect
approximation,
but you break it into
30 million pieces,
then you put the
pieces back together
in ways that make
a bit of sense,
and then you do interventions
to check that what you learned
is real.
So now--
[INAUDIBLE]
We always stumble upon complex
systems and emergent properties.
And then maybe this is
the biggest difficulty
in studying these
kind of systems.
And clearly, LLMs
they start displaying
this kind of behavior.
So if you start breaking
it down at the same time,
you end up losing those
emergent properties.
So how can you balance
that [INAUDIBLE]
using all these properties
that just emerged
when everything is together?
It's a good question.
So I think one thing
that makes LLMs different
is this flow of information
from the input to the output,
in which it seems like latent
spaces work at a higher
level of representation
or complexity
as you move through it.
And so all cells are
somehow like the same size.
They communicate
with each other,
but it's all like
lateral communication.
And I think you do see
this some in the brain
as you go from the first
light sensitive cells
through the visual cortex,
where you will get ultimately
like a cell, which is
sensitive to a particular face,
but that comes from
things sensitive to less
specific things and
ultimately things that
just detect edges and
shapes and those structures.
And so I think as you
move through that,
you do get these higher
levels of abstraction.
And so when I say
there's a feature that
seems to correspond
to errors in code,
this is one of our
atomic units, it's
one of the things we're
getting when we shatter.
This is like sensitive
to errors in code,
but in a very general way.
And so to some extent, I
think that these are built up
hierarchically, but that it's
just maybe they're still units.
There's another
thing that I think
we don't have any
traction on, which is like
if it's doing some in context,
like dynamical system stuff,
that I think that will be
much harder to understand.
And you might need much
larger ensembles of these.
OK.
Let's slideshow again.
So here's a medical exam style
differential diagnosis question.
32-year-old female at 30 weeks
gestation presents with severe
right-upper quadrant
pain, et cetera.
Given this context, if we could
only ask for one other symptom,
what should it be?
Does anybody-- is there
a doctor in the house?
Does anybody know what the
medical condition is here?
Yeah.
So ask about visual
disturbances.
And the reason is
because this is--
the most likely diagnosis
is preeclampsia here,
which is a severe
complication of pregnancy.
And we're able to trace through
by looking at these features
and how they're
grouping together
and how it flows that it's
pulling things from pregnancy
from that region, the headache,
the high blood pressure,
the liver tests to preeclampsia.
And then from that to other
symptoms of preeclampsia.
And then from those
ultimately, there's
actually two complete
visual disturbances.
And there's a tiny box here
showing what do we mean by that.
Those are-- this component is
also active on training examples
discussing causing vision
loss, floaters in the eye,
which is another
visual disturbance
lead to loss of vision.
The other answer
would be proteinuria.
And so it is in the same
way of thinking about Texas.
It's thinking about
preeclampsia in some way
before like saying
what these are.
And we can see that
intermediate state.
It is thinking about
other potential diagnoses
like biliary system disorders.
And if we suppress
the preeclampsia,
then it will say instead
of visual disturbances
with a rationale-- because
this presentation suggests
preeclampsia, it will
say decreased appetite
because the scenario
suggests biliary disease.
And so it is thinking
of these options.
When you turn one off, then
you get a coherent answer
consistent with the other one.
So does this mean, the fact
that you can intervene.
So clearly that this is only
represented in exactly one
location in the network, and
that by intervening there,
you don't need to intervene
in multiple places?
Well, so no.
Because two reasons--
three reasons.
The three reasons are one,
this node is a group of them.
It's a few of these
features that are all
related to preeclampsia.
The second is because it's
a cross layer transcoder.
Each of them writes
to many layers.
And then the third
is we're creaming it.
So here we're turning it double
the amount that it was on.
We overcorrect
and you often need
to do that to get
the full effect,
probably because there's
redundant mechanisms and stuff.
And so I don't think this is the
only place it is necessarily.
But it's enough.
Yeah.
Earlier in your talk
you talked a bit
about semanticity of neurons.
Yeah.
So for example, if you do one
of these interventions like
the pre-eclampsia and let's
say I deploy the model for some
other part, would
you expect like--
what is the distribution of
things that this will also hit
if you can give some sense of--
what would be the
adverse effect but what
would be other effects--
Yeah, that's a great question.
We didn't dig into
that as much here.
We did a little more
with our last paper.
I think that you push too
hard in the model goes off
the rails like in a big way.
Here this is less
for the purpose
of shaping model
behavior and more
for the purpose of validating
our hypothesis in this one
example.
So we were not like and now
let's take a model where
we've deleted this everywhere.
It's like, no,
the model is going
through answering this question.
Right here, we're turning
off this part of its brain,
and then we're
seeing what happens.
A couple questions on Zoom.
One is in practice when
you trace backwards
through these
features, do you see
a explosion of relevant features
as you go earlier in the model,
or is it some function of
distance from the output?
Yeah, the question
is like as you
go backwards through
the model, is the number
of relevant features go up?
Yes, sometimes you
do get convergence.
The early features might
be about a few symptoms
or something.
And those are quite important.
And I don't think
we've made a good plot
to answer that question.
I'm going to push
onwards a little bit
and I'll come back
to questions soon.
Got you.
Just one more.
How much are these examples
carefully selected or crafted?
Does this work for
most sentences?
You learn something about
most things you try.
So I'd say like 40% of
the prompts that we try,
we can see some non-trivial
part of what's going on.
It's not the whole picture.
And it sometimes doesn't
work, but it also
just takes 60 seconds of user
time to kick one of these off.
And then you wait
and then it's done.
And it comes back.
And then you get to learn
something about the model
rather than having to
construct a priori hypotheses
of what's going on.
You just get it.
Once you've built the
machine, you get it for free.
But this doesn't
tell you everything.
So here's a question like what
language are models thinking in?
If is-- is it a
universal language.
Is it English.
Is it like it just like
there's a French Claude
and a Chinese Claude
inside of Claude.
And who gets gated to is
depends on the question.
And so to answer this, we
looked at three sentences
which are the same sentence
in three languages.
So the opposite of small is big.
The [FRENCH].
And I can't speak
Mandarin but maybe
someone here can say
what someone surely
is a Mandarin
speaker in this room.
There's no chance.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Thank you.
[LAUGHTER]
I came to-- what's
the final character?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
I came to see it because
we were doing these,
like this part of the paper.
so many times.
It's the only character,
I can recognize now.
So this is even more
cartoony than the last one.
I'll get into the more
detailed version later.
But basically, what we
see is at the beginning
there are some of these
opposites in specific languages.
[FRENCH] in French,
opposite in English.
And the quotation,
it's like, this
is like an open quote in
the language I'm speaking.
So the quote that
follows will probably
be in the same language.
But then there's this complex
of features about antonyms
in many languages saying
large in many languages,
smallness in many
languages that go together.
And then you spit it back out
in the language of interest.
So the claim is that this
is a multilingual core here,
where smallness goes with
opposite to give you largeness
and then largeness plus--
this quote is in
English-- gives you
the word large largeness
plus this quote is in French
gives you [FRENCH].
We did a bunch of these
patching experiments.
You could say instead
of the opposite,
you could say a synonym of
and just like drop that in.
So the same thing
in all of them.
And now you'll get little
or minuscule in French.
And so patching in a
different state, you can--
it's the same feature you're
putting in these three places.
And you get the same
change in behavior later.
And we looked at this does
have a big effect with scale.
So you can look like how
many features overlap
between a pair of
sentences that are just
translations of each other as
you move through the model.
And at the beginning, it's just
the tokens in that language.
There's no overlap.
Mandarin when it's
tokenized, has
nothing in common with
English when it's tokenized.
So at the beginning and
the end, there's nothing.
But as you move
through the model,
you see a pretty large
portion of the components that
are active are the same
regardless of the language
that it was put in.
And so this is English Chinese,
French Chinese and English
French.
This is like a random baseline
if the sentences are unrelated.
So it's not just like the
middle is more common,
but when you compare pairs
that are translations,
this is in an 18-layer model.
And this is in our small
production model haiku.
So this generalization
is increasing with scale.
Yes.
So it's almost it can interpret
concepts in a multilingual--
Yes.
Have you ever tried
doing poems that
are metaphors that are
specific to that language, that
don't really have translation?
No, if you have some examples
of that, I'd love to try it.
I think that would be fun.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
Passage of time
and even feelings.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, I would be happy
for collaboration here.
Yes.
So would you say this
kind of implies that
in the center of the network is
the most abstract representation
of any given concept because--
I think I would basically
agree with this plot, which
is like a little to the
right of the center.
Yeah, at which point you
start to have to figure out
what to do with it,
because in the end,
the model has to say a thing.
And then have you seen if you
have a harder time finding
one of semantic features in the
middle of the network where it's
very abstract rather than
towards the end where
it's very concrete?
If anything, it's
actually the opposite.
Because the-- if you'll
permit me to be philosophical,
like the point of
a good abstraction
is that it applies
in many situations.
And so in the middle,
there should actually
be these common abstractions.
It's like dealing with
the very particulars
of this phrasing or this
grammar medical scenario,
that it's quite bespoke.
And so you would need way
more features to unpack it.
Yeah.
So one more question.
Yes.
Is the same like operation
stored redundantly
across multiple layers?
Do you find that, for example,
if you need five reasoning steps
to get something done for--
in one example, but
then in another example
you need eight reasoning
steps to get something done.
Do you redundantly have to
store the follow-up operation
on both of those layers?
Yeah, I think this is
like a very deep question.
So to repeat it
for the audience,
it's like, do we see redundancy
of the same operation
in many places.
And of course, this
it's like a thing
people complain about
with these models.
Which is like, well, if
it knows A and it knows B,
why can't it do them
in a row in its head.
And it might just literally be
that A is after B in its head
and it has to do a forward pass.
And so unless it gets
to think out loud,
it literally can't
compose those operations.
And you can see this
quite easily if you just
ask who is-- what's the birthday
of the father of the star
of the movie from 1921?
It might be able
to do all of those,
but it can't actually do all
those lookups consecutively.
That's like the first thing.
So there-- has to be redundancy.
And then we do see this.
It was one of the reasons
for the cross coder
setup is to try to zip up
some of that redundancy.
I think one of my
favorite plots is not
from the so-called
biology paper,
but is from the sister paper.
Here, let's find Copenhagen.
So on the left, if you do you
do this decomposition per layer
and on the right is you
do the cross layer thing
and basically, it's just
like bouncing back--
it's like the Copenhagen
is like propagated
and it's talking to
Denmark and it's just
happen in many
places in the model,
they all perform small
improvements to it.
There's another
perspective here,
which is like the neural ODE,
like gradient flow perspective,
where it's like all
tiny adjustments
in the same direction
all the time.
And I think the real models
are somewhere in between.
OK.
With the overlap of the features
here, as the models get larger,
you found if you change data
set very significantly or also
ordering in parts
of the data set,
you end up in very
different permutations.
We haven't done
systematic studies
of data set ordering effect.
I guess we're
talking about what's
machine fails and
sometimes I [INAUDIBLE].
I'm curious to hear
how [INAUDIBLE].
No, I don't think--
we've maybe been lucky.
You could have a plot
where it's like, how
compelling was the hypothesis
from the attribution graph.
And then, how well did it
work when you intervened?
And the best ones did work.
But there are some small
failure cases we talk about.
OK.
I want to dive into
the parallel motif
because I think it's
actually super interesting.
And it's a unique feature of
the transformer architecture.
It's massively parallel.
So to give a really
simple example of this.
Imagine that you want
to add 100 numbers.
So the easiest way to do
it is you start with one,
you add the next add
the next to the sum,
you add the next to the sum.
And you do 100 serial steps.
To do that with
a transformer, it
would need to be
100 layers deep.
But there's another
thing you can do,
which is could add pairs
consecutively in one layer
and then add the pairs
of pairs consecutively
in the next, and then the pairs
of those pairs in the next.
And so in log n depth, you
could add up the 100 numbers.
And given the depth
constraints here
and the sophistication of what
we ask these models to do,
it makes sense that
they would attempt
to do many things at once.
Pre-compute things you might
need, slap them all together.
And I'll give you a
few examples of this.
So if you ask the model to
add 36 and 59, it will say 95.
If you ask it how
it did that, it
will say use the
standard carrying
algorithm, which is not true.
What happens is
somewhat more like this.
So first it parses
out each number
into-- there's some component
where it's like literally 59,
but there's also something
for all numbers ending in 9
and something which is like
that number range and the same
up there.
And then you have
two streams, one
where it's getting the last
digit, right and then another
on top where it's getting
the magnitude, right.
And even inside the
magnitude, there's
a narrow band magnitude and
a really wide band magnitude.
And then those give
you a median band.
And then if the sum is in
this range and it ends in a 5,
then it's actually 95.
That narrows it down
and then it gives you
the answer, which is cool.
It's not how I would do it.
But then again, it wasn't
trained by a teacher being like,
here's something to do.
It just got whacked every
time it got it wrong
or rewarded every time it
got it right in training.
And I don't think we're going
to have this next in here.
So I want to show you
one of my favorite things
from the addition section, which
is OK there's a feature in here
If anybody here--
I feel like this is like a
word cell shape rotator test.
So for the shape rotators who
like mathematical thinking like
I love this section.
So this is the graphs
we make to visualize
on the arithmetic prompts.
This is like is it active on
the prompt A plus B for and B
and 1 to 100.
That's a grid.
And so vertical lines mean
like when the second operand is
in a range it's active.
These dots is like
is it a 6 and a 9.
So there's a grid, there's bands
a band here is a line x plus y
equals constant, right.
And so those are
where the sum is.
So we were looking at this
to figure out what these did.
But this feature here I
really like everything
in the graph you can
hover over, which is neat.
And see the feature.
And we looked at
cases in the data set
when this thing was active.
So on this narrow domain it's
active when things ending in 6
get added to things
ending in nine.
But on the data set it's active
in all these other cases.
So this is thymus
organ fragments,
federal proceedings volume 35.
It's like OK.
So in some sense that has to
be a 9 plus a 6 is the volume
35, supposedly if this
interpretation is correct,
here's just a list of numbers.
There's more journals.
There's these coordinates.
And so the claim here,
if our method is working
is that there's one component
that in this context
means ends in 6 plus ends in 6
But it's also active in these.
So this is really working
if secretly every one
of these examples is the
model adding a 6 to a 9.
And it's getting to reuse
the module for doing that
across those examples.
And so we dug in and--
I couldn't really
understand these.
So here's one example where
this is the token where
that feature was active.
And I just put it in Claude
and I was like, what is this?
And it's like this is a table
of astronomical measurements.
And it split it out in a
nicely formatted table.
And the first two columns
are the start and end
time of an observation period.
And this is the minutes of
an end time is predicting,
and if you read down the table,
the start to end interval
is like 38 minutes, 37
minutes, but it creeps up
over the course
of the experiment
to be like just
under 39 minutes.
And this measurement interval
started at a minute with a 6
and the 6 plus the 9
equals ending in a five.
And so the model was
just like cutting out
next token predictions for
arbitrary sequences of data
it was trained on.
And learned in that of course,
to recognize the context, what
it's supposed to do,
but then it needs
a bit where it has the
arithmetic table 6 plus 9.
You've just got to look it up.
So it has that somewhere.
And it's using that same lookup
in this very different context
where it needs to
add those things.
This was another one where it
turned out this was a table
and it's predicting this amount.
And these are
arithmetic sequences.
This is, I guess, the
total cost that's going up.
And so the amount that it's
going up by is this where
you're carrying-- that's about
9,000 plus 26,000 is 35,000.
This is maybe my favorite
where why is it firing
here to predict the year.
And the answer is
because it's volume 36.
This journal was founded in--
first edition was in 1960.
So the zero would have been in
1959 9 plus 59 plus 36 is 95.
And so it's using
the same little bit
to do the addition there.
And so I think when we
talk about generalization
and abstraction, this is--
for me like a pretty moving
example where I was like,
OK like did learn
this little thing,
but then using it
all over the place.
That's maybe not the most
mission critical thing
in the world.
So let's talk about
hallucinations.
So models, they're great.
They'll always
answering your question,
but sometimes they're wrong.
And that is just
because of pre-training.
They're meant to just predict
a plausible next thing.
Great.
It should say something.
If it knows nothing, it
should just give a name.
If it knows anything,
it should give
a name in the correct language.
If it knows more,
maybe a common name
from the era or just some
basketball player or whatever.
And so that's what
it's trained to do.
And then you're go to fine
tuning and you're like,
no, I want you to be an
assistant character, not just
a generic simulator.
And when you simulate
the assistant,
I want the assistant to say, I
don't know when the base model
certainty is somehow low.
And that's like a big
switch to try to make.
And so we were curious,
how does that happen?
How does this refusal to
speculate, get fine tuned in?
And then why does that fail?
And so here's two
prompts that get at this.
One is what sport does
Michael Jordan play?
Answer in one word,
it says basketball.
The other is what sport
does Michael Batkin play?
Which is just the person who
made up answer in one word
and it says, I apologize.
I can't find a definitive
record of a sports
figure named Michael Batkin.
So here this graph is
a little bit different.
They've got suppressive
edges highlighted here.
This is common in
neuroscience like inhibition.
And we've drawn
some features that
aren't active on this prompt but
are on this one and vice versa.
So if they're in gray, it
means it's inactive here.
But part of the reason
it's inactive in particular
is it's being suppressed by
something that is active.
And what we found
was this cluster
of four features in the middle.
Michael Jordan and then
we have a feature for it's
active when the models
recognizes answers to questions.
There's another feature
for unknown names.
And then there's a generic
feature for I can't answer that.
And that generic
feature I can't answer
is just fueled by the
assistant, which is always
on when the model is answering.
So it's just like
there's just an always
I don't know, to any question.
And then that gets
down modulated
when it recalls
something about a person.
So when Michael
Jordan is there, that
suppresses the unknown name,
boosts the known answer.
Both of those suppress
the can't answer
and that leaves room for the
path of actually recalling
the answer to come through.
And it can say basketball.
So that's a cool strategy.
But getting back to
model depth, there's
an interesting problem,
which is that it might
take a while for the model
to come up with an answer,
but it also would
have to at some point
decide to refuse
and get that going.
And those are
happening in parallel.
So you could have a little
bit of a mismatch where by--
it has to decide now whether or
not it's going to answer or not,
but it hasn't done all that it
can do to get a good answer.
And so you can get
some divergence
where for very hard
questions, for example.
But it still might know
it has to be like, OK, do
I think I'm going to get there.
And that's like a little
bit of a tricky knob.
It can't fully self-reflect on
the answer before saying it.
And so OK, this is
just the intervention.
You juice the
known answer and it
will hallucinate that
Michael Batkin plays chess.
So this is a fun one.
So if you ask for a paper
by Andrej Karpathy, formerly
of Stanford, it gives
a very famous paper
that he didn't write.
Why is that?
Well, it's like, trust
me, I've heard of Andrej
Karpathy from the name.
But then there's the part, which
is trying to recall the paper
and then it gives that answer.
And then actually it
says that and then
I think it's covered up here.
But then if you're
like are you sure.
It's like, no, I
don't really think
he wrote that because at that
point then the model as an input
gets both the
person and the paper
and can do calculation
earlier in the network again.
Now, we can juice this.
We can suppress the
known answer bit
and eventually it will
apologize and refuse.
There's a fun one
in the paper where
the model hasn't heard of me.
I didn't write that section.
Jack wrote that
section, and it refuses
to speculate about
papers I've written.
And then if you turn
off the unknown entity
and you give the
known answer, then
it says, I'm famous
for inventing
the [INAUDIBLE] principle,
which I hope to one day do.
OK.
So there's a lot more we
could talk about here.
I'm just going to speed
run these for vibes
and you can read the paper
where we do a lot more.
There's a jail breaks trying
to understand how they work.
And some of it is like you
get the model to say something
without yet recognizing
what it's saying.
And then once it's said
it, it's on that track.
And it has to balance being
coherent verbally with--
I shouldn't say that it takes a
while for it to cut itself off.
And we find that if we
suppress punctuation, which
would be an appropriate
grammatical time
to cut yourself off,
you can get it to keep
doing more of the jailbreak.
And that's a competing
mechanism thing.
There's a part,
which is recognizing,
what am I talking about?
What should I do?
And then there's a part,
which is completing it
and they're fighting
for who's going to win.
OK.
[INAUDIBLE]
Cool.
Let's talk about [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah OK.
So I think my family is
very disappointed if I
didn't talk about this one.
So this is a poem, a rhyming
couplet written by Claude.
He saw Carrot and
had to grab it.
His hunger was like
a starving rabbit.
It's good.
So how does it do this?
It's tricky because to
write a rhyming thing,
you better end with
a word that rhymes.
But you also need to have
it make semantic sense.
And if you wait to
the very end, you
can back yourself into a corner,
where there's no next word that
would be like metrically correct
and rhyme that would make sense.
Logically should be
thinking ahead a little bit
of where you're trying to go.
And we do see this.
So actually he saw carrot
and had to grab it; new line.
And so on that new line
token, it's actually--
there's a feature for
things rhyming with it.
So this is like after
words ending in it
or eaten poems and those feed
into rabbit and habit features.
And then the rabbit
feature is being
used to get starving and
then ultimately rabbit.
And we can-- we
can suppress these.
So if we suppress the
rhyming with it thing,
we get blabber,
grabber, salad bar.
And that's because of the
[INAUDIBLE] sound is still
there.
So it'll just like rhyme
with the [INAUDIBLE] part.
If we inject green, it
will now write a line
ending or rhyming with green,
sometimes ending with it.
If we put in a rhyme
with a different thing,
it'll go with e, I think.
I don't know if we have it here.
But if you just literally
suppress the rabbit,
it will make something ending
in habit when it rhymes.
And this was pretty neat.
This is like the smoking gun.
This is like oh, OK.
Literally, here is--
here's a model component.
When we look at the data set
examples when this is active,
it's literal instances of
the word rabbit and bunny.
A forward pass on this
model that feature
is active on the new line
at the end of the sentence.
And the model writes a
rhyme ending in rabbit.
And if we turn this off, then
it doesn't do that anymore.
So it's very definitely
thinking about that
is a place to take this.
And then that influences
the line that's coming out.
And so that's a place where
even though it's saying one
token at a time.
It's like has done some
planning in some sense,
here's a target
destination and then
writing something to writing
something to get there.
There's equivalent things.
There's an incredible
thing with unfaithfulness.
I'll just say sometimes
the model is lying to you.
And if you look at how
it got to its answer,
you can tell, in this
case, it's using a hint
and working backwards
from the hint
so that it's math answer
will agree with you.
And you can tell because
you can literally see--
you can see it taking
your hint, which
is the number 4, working
backwards to divide
by 5 to give you a 0.8.
So when you multiply
by 5, you will get 4
and it will agree with you,
which is not what you want.
What you would want is something
like this, where it is only
using information from
the question to give you
the answer to the question.
But if you just look
at the explanations,
they look the same.
They look like it's
doing math, right.
And so here there's
a competing thing of
should I use the
hint, which would have
made sense in pre-training.
It would let you guess
the answer better
and you're rewarded if
you say the next token.
Well, so maybe the humans.
And you should use the hint.
Should I do the math actually?
And these are
competing strategies.
They're happening at the
same time on the right.
This one wins.
[INAUDIBLE] makes it one
strategy or the other.
How does that work?
Yeah.
They're both available.
Yes.
How is it coming to
this-- like, obviously
there's no time constraint.
Yes.
Is there some other incentive
or motivation driving that?
I think that's the question.
So I think in this
paper we really
did we were able to say
which strategies were used
when it got to this answer.
But the why, I don't think
we've really nailed down.
I think that to
some extent it could
be we could look at some
of this more carefully.
I think in the hallucination
case, we had a bit of a hint.
It was like
recognizing the entity.
So I'm going to do the refusal
thing or let it through.
Here, though, my
strong suspicion
is that it's just doing both.
But in a case where it's
more confident in one answer
that shouts louder so it doesn't
know what the cosine of this is.
So all that's left is
following the hint.
But I think a big
caveat is that we're not
modeling attention
at all, and attention
is very good at selecting.
You've got this [INAUDIBLE].
That's like a bilinear thing.
You can really pick with that.
And we're not modeling how
those choices are made.
So I wouldn't be surprised if
for a lot of these attention
is crucially involved in
choosing which strategy to use,
while the MLPs are heavily
involved in executing
on those strategies.
And in that case,
we'd be totally
blind to what's going on here.
I've been mulling on
this idea for a while.
How do we prevent [INAUDIBLE]?
I mean, that's like
$1 billion question.
I think if I literally
knew the answer to that
and it worked really
well, I couldn't tell you.
I would just go make Claude
the best model in the world
because it's always accurate.
But I don't know the
answer, so I can speculate.
I mean, I think it
is in some sense
an impossible problem
for exactly this reason.
And so I think you could
try to train better and have
the models be better calibrated
on their self knowledge.
You could, I think,
with the thinking tags
basically with the
reasoning models
is a straightforward
way where you
do let the model check things.
And I think models are
much better on reflection
than they are on
the forward pass,
because I think one forward
pass is just limited
for these physical reasons.
I think as an effective strategy
that might be more the way
than not allowing like how
do you keep the creativity.
And another possibility is you
could make the model dumber
somehow.
So maybe you could
make a model which
doesn't hallucinate, but is
just dumber because it uses
a bunch more capacity
just for checking itself
in the forward pass.
And it could be when
models are smart enough,
people might take
that trade off.
Do you think that the underlying
architecture, the transformer
architecture--
Yeah, I think that's
one of the things here.
It's possible that with
the recurrent thing,
you could just give it a few
more loops to check stuff.
I mean, if you could
fully adaptive compute,
you could just have it go until
it's some level of confident,
right.
And get variable
compute per token.
And then bail, if it's not.
I think there is a trick
thing about hallucination.
It's like people think of it as
being like a well-defined thing,
but it's producing like reams of
text, which word is the one that
went wrong, and there are
some very factual questions
where that's true.
But I think if you
think more generally,
what would make a given
token a hallucination,
it's a little bit less clear.
I want to just see if
there's anything-- yeah OK.
So there's nothing else here
other than if you want more,
read the stuff.
And I guess this
probably ends formally
in two or three minutes.
Is that-- yeah.
So I will just be done now
and then people can clap
and people can
leave if they want.
But I will just stay for
questions for a while,
and I'm happy to
continue doing questions
as long as people want.
So thank you.
[APPLAUSE]